גוט טוב gut tov and שנה טובה. shana tova. We pick up
today at today's דף daf is דף ט׳, daf tes, nine. We
are all caught up. We pick up at the bottom of ח׳
עמוד ב׳ ches amud bais and we are in the middle of
a discussion about whether somebody riding an animal, and as explained in
the גמרא gemara and it really means sitting on an animal and
holding onto the reins, is that a קנין? kinyan? Number one, is
רוכב, rocheiv, I say רוכב, rocheiv, the גמרא's gemara לשון lashon is
רכוב, rachuv, I don't know why, but anyway, anyway, is רוכב rocheiv
a קנין? kinyan? And if it is, how does it fare when
it's competing against מנהיג, manhig, the guy who's leading it? But if
the person does what we normally call riding, sitting and making the
animal move by, you know, by kicking it with his legs or
something, then that's considered a case of מנהיג ברגליו manhig b'raglav and
that certainly is a קנין. kinyan. But the question is when it
comes by רוכב rocheiv by itself, just sitting on the animal and
holding the reins. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says two lines
from the bottom on ח׳ עמוד ב׳, ches amud bais, תא שמע,
ta shma, come and hear, שנים שהיו מושכין בגמל ומנהיגין בחמור. shnayim
she'hayu moshchin bagamal umanhigin bachamor. If you have two people, this is
similar like another scenario similar to the opening משנה mishna of our
פרק, perek, except our משנה mishna had two people riding, or one
person riding and one person leading, and this has the difference between
a case about מושכין בגמל, moshchin bagamal, dragging a camel, because by
a camel the person would walk in front and the camel would
walk behind, so you'd drag the camel as it were, that's the
word משיכה, meshicha, ומנהיגין בחמור, umanhigin bachamor, and leading a donkey. I
guess in a donkey you'd walk either to the side or behind.
Does anybody know?
Do they use like a little like switch to push them along
from behind? I feel like I've seen a movie.
Okay, so they're like walking behind.
We need a field trip to the Bronx Zoo where they have
camels. You can't walk directly behind a camel either.
No, you walk in front of the camel. You're מושך moshich the
camel. Directly behind and lead it. All right, whatever, towards the back
and to the side. Okay, so anyway, so whether they were leading
the donkey or walking
to the side of the donkey, which is the normal way in
which you would lead those animals, או היה אחד מושך ואחד מנהיג,
o hayah echad moshich ve'echad manhig, or let's say within the same
animal, one was leading in front and one was hitting from behind.
So you might think in that case, well, maybe the person who's
doing the more natural thing for that animal, that should be the
better קנין kinyan or the better חזקה chazaka because here they're competing
in terms of who took possession of it. So במדה זו קנו,
bemidah zo kanu, no, in this way they are קנו, kanu, which
means that even if it is, they're competing with one another, and
one is more natural, nevertheless they're both a good קנין, kinyan, so
even the less natural one is a קנין kinyan and they would
both be קונה koneh in this case. רבי יהודה אומר, rebbi yehuda
omer, רבי יהודה rebbi yehuda says, לעולם לא קנו עד שתהא משיכה
בגמל והנהגה בחמור. le'olam lo kanu ad she'tehay meshicha bagamal vehanhaga bachamor.
No, the only קנין kinyan that works is the natural one, leading
the camel or walking behind the donkey. Whenever I learn this גמרא
gemara I can't stop, I always think about
the Push-Me-Pullyu, do people remember that? From Dr. Dolittle, the one with,
anyway, the two, whatever, I forget what it was, but the animal
that had to be led in one way and led in the
other. Anyway, fine.
Okay, so
תני מיהת, tani mihas, we teach nonetheless, או היה אחד מושך ואחד
מנהיג, o hayah echad moshich ve'echad manhig, the
most options it gives you for being קונה koneh this animal
is drawing, you know, dragging it, leading from in front or leading
from the side. אין, in, that works, אבל רכוב לא, aval rachuv
lo, it sounds like just sitting on the animal would not be
a קנין. kinyan. So the גמרא gemara says no, הוא הדין דאפילו
רכוב, hu hadin d'afilu rachuv, even sitting on the animal would be
a קנין, kinyan, והא דקתני מושך ומנהיג, ve'ha d'ktani moshich u'manhig, so
why did it give those examples? לאפוקי מדברי רבי יהודה, l'apukei m'divrei
rebbi yehuda,
for the obvious reason, because רבי יהודה rebbi yehuda is going to
say it has to be the natural way, viz., the leading of
the camel and
the walking besides the donkey. So the תנא קמא tanna kamma is
saying, I don't care which one you do, you know, and even
the better one, and even the more natural one doesn't win out
over the less natural one. קמשמע לן דאפילו איפכא נמי קני, kamashma
lan d'afilu ipcha nami kani, even if you reverse it, קני. kani.
אי
הכי, ei hachi, if that's
true, וערבינהו וליתנינהו, v'arbineihu v'lisnineihu,
why separate them off? Why not just, you know, sort of put
it all in one cholent and say שנים שהיו מושכין ומנהיגין, shnayim
she'hayu moshchin u'manhigin, if two people were leading or were, you know,
from in front or were directing from behind or driving, maybe that
would be a good word for מנהיג, manhig, to drive, בין בגמל
בין בחמור, bein bagamal bein bachamor, whether a camel or a donkey,
you know, either way it works. Why not just put it all
together? Why separate it off to say this is the natural way
for the camel, this is the natural way for the donkey? So
the גמרא gemara says no, איכא חד צד דלא קנו, ika chad
tzad d'lo kanu, because there would be one way, because there would
be one way in which it wouldn't work. Which would be the
one way it wouldn't work? איכא דאמרי משיכה בחמור, ika d'amri meshicha
bachamor,
either the dragging of the donkey.
or the driving of the camel. What does that mean? It means
that the משנה mishnah. *Mishna*, the ברייתא brayta, *Beraita* set up and
said if you drag the camel or drive the donkey or if
in one animal one person is dragging and one person is driving.
Okay,
but what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is saying is one of those
animals, it's not telling us which is which, one of those animals
either type of קנין kinyan *kinyan* works. But the other one actually
doing the less natural thing doesn't work. Okay, now it's not telling
us which is which. Okay, it might be saying if it's a
camel, then whether you're driving or whether you're leading it works. Okay,
or it might be saying if it's a donkey, whether you're driving
or leading it works. But one of those animals doing the unnatural
thing does not work. Okay, and that's why it says במידה זו
*bemida zo*. It has to be this way. Of course, it's very
troublesome, you know, you say it has to be exactly this way
but you're not being clear what that way is. Okay, but that's
what it's saying. It's not all one big טשולנט *cholent*. It's not
that it doesn't matter at all. There is one animal that doing
it one way, the not natural way for that animal doesn't work,
but it's not clear which is which.
Is the תנא *Tanna* telling us the one that doesn't work is
משיכה meshicha בחמור *meshicha bachamor* and הנהגה בגמל *hanooga begamal*?
No, that's what רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says. רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*
says if it's the unnatural thing for either animal it doesn't work.
Whereas the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* is clearly saying that you could
do both types of things for one animal and it could work,
either type of thing for one animal could work. But what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is that the exclusive word במידה זו
*bemida zo*, the this way, which seems to say there's another way
that it doesn't work, has nothing to do with רוכב rochev *rochev*.
The other way that it doesn't work is the unnatural thing for
the other animal, but it's not telling us which is which, which
is not so helpful from a הלכה halacha? *halachic* point of view.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אי איתימא מסיפא
*ee iteima meseifa*, some ask this from the end of this ברייתא
braita. *Beraita*, okay, not from the first part where it says רוכב
rochev *rochev* or מנהיג manhig, *manhig*, but the second part where it
says במידה זו *bemida zo*. Okay, and not רוכב rochev *rochev*, excuse
me, מושך moshech *moshech* or מנהיג manhig *manhig*. אי איתימא לסיפא *ee
iteima leseifa*, במידה זו קנה kana. *bemida zo kana*, this is the
way that you do the קנין kinyan. *kinyan*. במידה זו למעוטי מאי
*bemida zo lemaoti mai*, what does that exclude? That seems to be
only this way, and since the ברייתא Beraisa *Beraita* seemed to allow
doing the reverse, what's it coming to exclude? So למעוטי מאי *lemaoti
mai*, לאו למעוטי רכוב rochov *lav lemaoti rachuv*, isn't it coming to
exclude a case of a guy just sitting on the animal? לא
למעוטי איפכא *lo lemaoti ipcha*, no, it's coming to exclude reversing it,
doing the not natural way. אי הכי I hachi היינו רב יהודה
*ee hachi haynu Rav Yehuda*, that's what רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says.
רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says it has to be the natural way
of leading or driving. לא איכא בינייהו צד אחד דלא קני kni.
*lo ika beineihu tzad echad delo kani*, no, no, no, the תנא
קמא *Tanna Kamma* clearly allows you in one of the animals to
do the unnatural one, but the other animal it doesn't. איכא דאמרי
משיכה meshicha, בחמור *ika de'amrei meshicha bachamor*, some say the one thing
that doesn't work is dragging the donkey. ואיכא דאמרי הנהגה בגמל *ve'ika
de'amrei hanooga begamal*, no, it's driving the camel. Okay, anyway, whatever it
is, they're here talking about the fact what the relative benefit of
driving versus leading when it's the not natural thing for the animal,
but they are completely not relating to the question of רוכב rochev
*rochev*. Okay, that ברייתא braita, *Beraita* is irrelevant to רוכב rochev *rochev*,
nobody was even talking or thinking about it. The issue there was
if you do the way of getting the animal to move in
a not natural way, would that still be a קנין kinyan. *kinyan*
or not? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this,
תא שמע ta shema. *ta
shma*, let's try to prove the רוכב *rochev* issue yet again. אחד
רוכב חמור ואחד תופס במוסירה *echad rochev chamor ve'echad tofus bemosira*, here
you've got a ברייתא *Beraita* that explicitly deals with sitting on the
donkey. Now of course anytime it says רוכב *rochev*, you don't know
if they're talking about just sitting or what the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
calls מנהיג ברגליו manhig beraglav, *manhig beraglav*, what we would call riding,
having it move, which then would be more obvious. So we'll see,
but we're going to assume it means just sitting and is relevant
for our discussion. So yes?
I don't understand the underpinnings of this whole conversation. Wouldn't one think
that you make a קנין kinyan *kinyan* by demonstrating control over the
animal? And getting it to move anyway under your direction would seem
to be adequate no matter how you
did it?
You're talking about the הנהגה *hanooga* versus the משיכה meshicha *meshicha* issue?
Anything. Pulling it, dragging it, leading it.
Just if it moves. I don't know. Really? Really? I would say
the opposite. I would say like, you know, like if I don't
know what I am doing with the thing, okay, I'm reminded of
the time when I once went when Dvora and I were on
vacation and we were at some Greek island or whatever and we
rented motorized scooters and neither of us knew what the heck we
were doing and we were on it for about two seconds and
it sort of went out from under us and the guy said
give them back to me, I'm canceling the rent. So anyway, so
you can get it to move and not know what you're doing
and do it in a bizarre way that doesn't demonstrate בעלות *ba'alus*,
that demonstrates like incompetence, you know? So for that presumably is the
debate between רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* and the חכמים *Chachamim*, you know.
So incompetence is not קנין kinyan *kinyan*.
Right. Okay. I mean there are incompetent owners, I'm sure that's true.
Okay, but I'm not sure that just getting it to move in
a way that doesn't show you really understand it and know how
to use it is a demonstration of ownership. All right, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this, תא שמע *ta shma*, אחד רוכב חמור ואחד תופס במוסירה *echad
rochev chamor ve'echad tofus bemosira*. The bridle, yeah, although I think it
sounds more when it speaks about handing it over that you're talking
about the reins, but anyway, זה קנה חמור וזה קנה מוסירה. ze
kana chamor ve'ze kana mosira. So the guy on the donkey, that's
a קנין kinyan. on the donkey, holding the reins as we discussed
before is like hand over the reins, the act of handing over
is a קנין. kinyan But if you find a lost object, a
donkey, and you grab the reins, grabbing the reins is not a
קנין. kinyan A קנין kinyan is משיכה meshichah, making it move or
we're discussing רוכב sitting on it, but grabbing the reins for a
lost object is not a קנין kinyan on the animal. Okay, it
needs to be handed over by the owner. So therefore in this
case, I jumped on the donkey and you grabbed the reins, I
am קונה koneh the donkey and you're קונה koneh the reins. Okay,
זה קנה חמור וזה קנה מוסירה. שמע מינה Shema mina so you
hear from this, רכוב קני. rochov kani. Look, if just sitting on
it is a קנין. kinyan, So that's of course you can never
really prove it, דהכי נמי dehachi nami במנהיג ברגליו. bemanhig beraglav. Who
says we're talking about just sitting on it, we're talking about what
we would call riding, you're using your legs and you're getting it
to move, so therefore that's a קנין kinyan of מנהיג, manhig, that's
a קנין kinyan of leading, a קנין kinyan of משיכה, meshichah that's
not the רכוב rachuv that you're asking about. Okay, אי הכי ei
hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara if you're talking about a real קנין
kinyan of מנהיג manhig? like something we know is a good strong
קנין, kinyan נקני נמי רכוב במוסירה. nikni nami rochov bemosira. Why does
the guy who's riding it not also get the reins? Now why
should he get the reins? Is it because he's considered to be
like doing a משיכה meshichah on the reins that he gets the
animal to move, he's causing the reins to move a little with
him? Is it because the reins are considered to be one unit
together with the animal and if you're קונה koneh the animal you're
קונה koneh the reins? So we'll see about that in a little
while the גמרא's Gemara going to discuss if you do a קנין
kinyan on the animal, are you automatically קונה koneh the objects that
are on the animal. Even there there are differences, there's like if
the animal is carrying like a donkey has saddlebags and it's got
wares on it, that is conceptually distinct, it's being carried by the
donkey. So being קונה koneh the donkey doesn't necessarily mean let's say
it was a הפקר hefker donkey and in it it had sacks
that had stuff in it. Is the קנין kinyan on the donkey
a קנין kinyan on the sacks, right, or do we say no,
those are conceptually separate things and you need a separate קנין kinyan.
on the sacks? But here the bridle certainly logically would be considered
to be one. Okay, so
let's so anyway that's גמרא's Gemara question, if you're doing a קנין
kinyan on the donkey why are you not also קונה koneh the
reins? So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא ela fine says the גמרא, Gemara אימא זה קנה חמור וחצי
מוסירה וזה קנה חצי מוסירה. eima ze kana chamor vechatzi mosira veze
kana chatzi mosira. Fine,
let's switch the גרסא girsa of the ברייתא, if it weren't enough
to say you get the donkey and he gets the reins, we're
going to say you get the donkey and half of the reins,
and the other guy gets the half of the reins, okay, or
the bridle whichever it is.
So you each get half. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
that doesn't make sense either. בשלמא רכוב קני, Bishlama rochov kani, I
get why the guy on the donkey is קונה koneh half, דקא
מגבה ליה בן דעת. deka magbe lei ben daat. We're getting back
to the case of two people picking up a מציאה metzia at
the same time, right, where so this is again it's not exactly
clear what קנין kinyan we're conceptualizing the person on the donkey doing.
Like the person who picks up the reins, he's doing a הגבהה.
hagbah. Okay, he's picking the reins off the ground, right, you know,
but it's only הגבהה hagbah half because the other half of the
reins is attached to the bridle on the donkey. He didn't pick
that up, that was always suspended. Okay, so we're going to ask
what type of a קנין kinyan is it that I picked the
reins off the ground, I didn't pick the entire thing, I picked
the part that was on the ground off the ground but the
other part was already suspended. Okay, so why does he get anything?
Alright, so let's take a look.
The guy, the other guy meanwhile is sitting on the
בהמה behema because he
or he's riding the בהמה behema
because he's attached to the reins.
Yeah, so he's doing a קנין kinyan on the בהמה, behema, he's
getting the בהמה behema to move, he's מנהיג ברגליו, manhig b'raglav.
so we get that he gets the reins. Okay, now why does
he get the reins if the other guy's holding on to half
of it? So that could be again if they were both קונה
koneh you could say they're both doing it for themselves and for
one another. So right like we said before, even if they're not
intending to, we define it as if they're doing that. Okay, but
let's take a look. גמרא Gemara's says like this: בשלמא רכוב קני,
Bishlama rochov kani, I get why the guy on the donkey gets
half the reins, דקא מגבה ליה בן דעת. deka magbe lei ben
daat. The guy who picked it up could be understood to be
picking it up for himself and for the guy on the donkey
if that's a necessary part of him being קונה. koneh. אלא תפוס
במוסירה במאי קני? Ela tafus bemosira bemai kani? But how about does
the guy on the reins קונה? koneh? Okay, so
now again like why it assumes that the guy riding on the
donkey isn't also doing his half to help the guy with the
reins, it could be that the גמרא Gemara just understands it's like
you're mixing and matching different things. The guy who picks up the
reins is doing a קנין הגבהה. kinyan hagbah. The guy on the
donkey might be causing the reins to move if he's getting the
donkey to move, right, but that's not a קנין הגבהה. kinyan hagbah.
So still the guy on the floor did not do a full
קנין הגבהה, kinyan hagbah, he only picked up half an object. Picking
up half and having the other half moved because the donkey is
moving does not combine to make a whole קנין. kinyan, Okay, but
I still don't get how combines in the opposite direction. I'm getting
the donkey to move and the other guy is holding it. Why
does that combine to make me קונה? koneh? So it's not exactly
clear to me why the גמרא Gemara understands that the קנין kinyan
done by the guy picking up the reins helps for the guy
on the donkey but not vice versa.
I understand. I just don't understand why the גמרא Gemara understands there
to be an asymmetry. Why does your picking up the reins help
me, but my riding the donkey doesn't help you? Okay?
Why do you need help if you're riding the donkey?
Well because I have
the other guy's half of the reins.
Right. So meaning if you understand—part of this question is why are
we assuming that I own the reins? Is it because I make
the reins move? If it's I make the reins move, I do
need help because you're sort of holding on to them and not
letting them move from their place. Okay. But if it's because it's
one package with the donkey, and if I'm קונה koneh the donkey
I'm קונה koneh the reins, then I certainly don't need help. But
that's the way the גמרא Gemara frames it. The גמרא Gemara's frames
it is you're picking up the reins, we get why that helps
me, which assumes like I need it to help me.
Okay. But then why does my riding of the donkey help you?
But I don't get it. Like if your הגבהה hagbahah can help
my משיכה, meshichah why can't my משיכה meshicha help your הגבהה? hagbahah?
Like I really don't get the asymmetry. And your question I also—it's
a good question. Why do I even need your הגבהה hagbahah especially
if you conceptualize it as one package? So I don't understand what's
getting—what sort of how the גמרא's Gemara understanding the problem. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara answers. Okay,
so the
גמרא Gemara's says, אימא זה קנה חמור וכולה מוסירה וזה קנה מה
שתפוס בידו. Eima zeh kanah chamor v’kulah mosira v’zeh kanah mah she’tafus
b’yado. Fine, completely changed the גירסא girsa of the ברייתא. The guy
on the donkey gets the donkey and the bridle and the reins;
it's like one package. Okay. And again, that makes sense if, you
know, as Jenna's pointing out, if you consider it one package, I
don't need the other guy's help at all. Since I'm קונה koneh
the donkey I get everything. And the thing that the guy who
picked up the reins, the only thing he gets is what's in
his hand, because we said before what's in your hand is like
it's cut off. So that you did a full
קנין kinyan? on even if you didn't do a קנין kinyan, on
the rest of the reins. Okay. וזה קנה מה שתפוס בידו. v’zeh
kanah mah she’tafus b’yado. גמרא Gemara says one minute, האי מאי, hai
mai, what sense does this make? אם תמצי לומר מגביה מציאה לחברו
קנה חברו, Im timtzei lomar magvia metzia l’chavero kanah chavero, if we
say that you could pick up something for your friend a lost
object and he could own it,
when is that true? קנה חברו, kanah chavero, הני מילי היכא דקא
מגבה לה אדעתא דחבריה. hani mili heicha d’ka magbah lah ada'ata d’chavrei.
That's if I see this nice lost object, I see this wallet
in the street, the owner twenty bucks or whatever in the street,
and I have—figure I'm going to do it for Charlie, I like
Charlie, and I intentionally do it for Charlie. האי, Hai, this guy,
right, when each one is picking it up, they really only want
it for themselves. If they're doing it for the other person, it's
only because being קונה koneh for the other person is necessary to
let them be קונה koneh for themselves. האי, Hai, in this case,
אדעתא דידיה קא מגבה לה. ada'ata d’didei ka magbah lah. You're taking
it up for yourself. So the guy who picks up the reins,
so איהו לא קני, ihu lo kani, if he's not going to
get the reins, he's only going to get what's in his hand,
אחריני מקני, achrinei makni, then he wouldn't want the guy on the
donkey to get the reins; he's not picking it up on behalf
of the guy on the donkey. So you see, Jenna, unfortunately not
like you wanted to say, that the גמרא Gemara is consistent with
what it assumed before, that somehow it seems you need the picking
up that's being done by the guy to help the guy on
the donkey. So it's not like he gets it as a package
together with the donkey. But again, what I still don't get is
why can a הגבהה hagbahah help me with my משיכה meshicha. on
the reins but my משיכה meshicha, can't help the guy with his
הגבהה? hagbahah? I'm not exactly sure how that works, but that's the
גמרא's Gemara question. So your הגבהה, hagbahah, if you're not going to
get part of the reins, you're not going to do it for
me. Okay. And therefore, so the גמרא Gemara winds up—it's just like
the גמרא Gemara sort of did this before—it doesn't allow for asymmetry.
As soon as you introduce asymmetry, then I'm not going to do
what I need to do for you if you're not helping me
out either. Okay, one minute, so the גמרא's Gemara answer is אמר
רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, fine,
let's try to switch it a third time. זה קנה חמור בי
פגיה—this Zeh kanah chamor bi pageiha one gets the donkey and like
the—you know, this is I think the bridle, the thing directly on
the, you know, the bit in the mouth of the donkey. Okay,
that is one unit with the donkey or that maybe is independent
from the reins and doesn't need the assistance of the guy with
the reins. וזה קנה מה שתפוס בידו. v’zeh kanah mah she’tafus b’yado.
The other guy gets the part that's in his hand itself; that's
like it's cut off. Each one gets the piece that's considered sort
of totally theirs, unrelated to the rest. Okay, והשאר, v’hashaar, the reins
in the middle that are now suspended in air—one guy has a
hand, the other guy has the bridle—the real reins, the rest of
the reins are suspended in mid-air. In that case, לא קנה לא
זה ולא זה, lo kanah lo zeh v’lo zeh, neither one gets
it. Since the guy picking it up does not get—is not able
to get assistance from the guy on the donkey, the guy on
the donkey's קנין kinyan. doesn't help for the guy picking it up,
for whatever reason. הגבהה Hagbahah needs another part הגבהה; hagbahah; it needs
the other part lifted up. The other part being moved doesn't work.
So since he's not getting his half, he's not doing what he
needs to help the other guy get his half, and therefore the
stuff in the middle remains ownerless. Okay. And anybody can come and
grab the reins in the middle. Clear to everybody? Okay, we're back
to our asymmetry from before. Anyway, we have not resolved the question
about רוכב and whether that works. Yes?
I just had a thought, there is a difference. In other words,
I'm the guy on the ground. I pick up the piece of
the reins. Right in my hand. Right. And the guy on the...
on the animal, it's like a גרמא, grama, like, in other words,
he's not directly touching those reins. Directly holding it. Only אגב הבהמה.
agav habiheima. Right, so that's the difference between the two, right? That's
it again?
And therefore what? Therefore he... who should be... I don't understand. So
but that... I don't understand why that explains the asymmetry in the
direction it works. Why does your הגבהה hagbah not help me? My
moving it can help you, but your הגבהה... hagbah... I think it's
because הגבהה, hagbah, for it to be a הגבהה, hagbah, you need
to say both all parts of the object were lifted off the
ground. And at the end of the day, the fact that it
was already suspended and I just moved the part that was suspended,
you cannot conceptualize that as a הגבהה hagbah because, you know, the
whole object was not lifted up. Whereas if I'm doing the משיכה
meshichah and making it move and you're doing the הגבהה hagbah from
that perspective, it's like, you know, all parts of the object are
moving. One's moving vertically, you know, horizontal and the other's somehow moving
vertical. Somehow those two are understood as combining.
It's like you're riding the animal and you like kick it and
it takes off, it's going to take the reins with it. Right.
But if I'm just here moving the reins up and down, that's
not necessarily moving the animal.
Right. But that would be why my moving could work by itself.
It still doesn't exactly explain why it needs your assist, right? It
would move without...
it's attached to the animal. It's not moving. Right.
So the fact that you're assisting somehow... you're saying the fact that
you're lifting it up somehow... if you weren't lifting it up without
intending to assist, then the move... it wouldn't be able to move
forward, you would hold it back. But the fact that you're willing
to assist, lift it up. So what you're saying is you're trying
to see the הגבהה hagbah as like a virtual משיכה. meshichah Like
the fact that you're lifting it up is somehow read as a
willingness to move it forward, somehow as if I'm moving it forward,
right? Because if I'm not holding it, lifting it up, but I'm
holding it tight, you're still being... you're still limited to how far
you can go, right? It's still not exactly clear. But somehow הגבהה
hagbah requires both parts lifted up, but משיכה, meshichah if I'm moving
forward, a little assist from you is enough to help. It's not
exactly clear why they understand the asymmetry. Anyway, let's take now an
attempt to restore the ברייתא to its original meaning. אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי, Rav Ashi, I'm sorry I just
read that, רב אבהו... Rav Abbahu... and רב אבהו Rav Abbahu says,
לעולם כדקתני, le'olam kede'katani, really it's like it said originally. The guy
lifting it up gets the whole reins even though he only lifted
up half of the half of the reins, the other half was
already suspended. הב יכול לנתקו ולהביאו אצלו. hov yachol lenatko ulhavi'o etzlo.
הגבהה hagbah on half of the object is good if the other
half is suspended. Why? Because you could yank it and bring the
whole thing to you. Now, what does that mean? רשי Rashi understands
that this would be true even if the whole object was started
on the ground. If I lift up part of an object, and
imagine just a little piece of it is on the ground and
I could do a yank, you know, and with my yank... I
haven't done the yank, but I could do a yank and the
rest would lift off, then it's like I've already lifted it all
off the ground. So whether it all starts on the ground or
part starts suspended, רשי Rashi just says it's easier if it's suspended.
If it's... if you imagine like a big טלית talis or a
big rein, and you do a yank, right, so if it was
a big טלית talis and most was on the ground and I
did a yank, it wouldn't all come off. But if it starts
suspended and I did a yank, right, then it really... then it
does all get off, right? Once it gets off the table it's
suspended on, it remains all in mid-air for a brief moment before
it falls down. But רשי Rashi understands that whether it's starting suspended
or not, according to רב אבהו, Rav Abbahu, if you lift up
part of the object and in theory if you just did a
yank you could get it all off the ground, it's like you
lifted it all off the ground. One could argue that רב אבהו's
Rav Abbahu only saying this when part of the object started off
the ground. Because if you think about it, right, I lifted part,
the whole object is currently off the ground and the fact that
I didn't lift that other part off the ground, it started that
way, well, if I can yank it that makes it enough like
it's all part of my act, you know? So it's not clear
to me that רב אבהו Rav Abbahu would say the same if
it all started on the ground. But either way, רב אבהו Rav
Abbahu is saying I don't need the assist of the guy on
the donkey. I lifted up my half, in theory I could yank
it. Okay, maybe it wasn't attached to the donkey's mouth, I don't
know if this requires the guy who lifted up the
reins... I don't know if this needs the fact that were it
not on the donkey, you know, attached to the bridle, like, you
know, because if it is attached to the bridle, I don't think
it's going to work. But anyway, he says that is enough of
a קנין הגבהה. kinyan hagbah. You lift half of it off the
ground, the other half is suspended, that's enough of a קנין הגבהה.
kinyan hagbah. And that's why the guy on the ground does not
need the assist of the other guy. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says הב יכול לנתקו ולהביאו אצלו, hov yachol lenatko ulhavi'o etzlo, that
seems like a pretty reasonable answer. The גמרא Gemara, does not like
it. תדי רב אבהו בדשותיה Tadi Rav Abbahu Brushi or בדשותיה, Bedushi,
that's רב אבהו's Rav Abbahu statement, that's wrong or that's a joke
depending on what your גרסא girsa is. Okay, דאי לא תימא הכי,
d'ilo teima hakhi, if you don't say it's a joke, if you
say רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu is right, I'm going to do a
reductio ad absurdum now. It's not so absurd, but here's what the
גמרא Gemara says: טלית שמקצתה חציה גבי קרקע וחציה גבי עמוד, talis
shemiktzaso chetzyo gabei karka vechetzyo gabei amud, if you think you have
a cloak that's half on the ground and half on a table
or you know on some type of a pillar,
ובא אחד והגביה חציה מן הקרקע, uva echad vehigbia chetzyo min hakarka,
somebody lifted up half from the ground, ובא אחר והגביה חציה מן
גבי עמוד, uva acher vehigbia chetzyo min gabei amud, and somebody else
took half off of the like the pillar, הכא נמי דקמא קני
ובתרא לא קני, hacha nami d'kama kani vebasra lo kani, would you
say the first one was קונה koneh and not the last one?
הואיל ויכול לנתקו ולהביאו אצלו, hoil veyachol lenatko ulehivio etzlo, just 'cause
he could yank it and bring it to himself? אלא הדרא בה
רבי אבהו, ella hadra beh Rabbi Abahu, so clearly Rabbi Abahu is
wrong. Of course תוספות Tosafot says, yeah and what's so absurd about
that? Like why not? That's as reasonable as the other thing. If
you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, דאי לא תימא הכי,
d'ilo teima hakhi, this low תוספות, Tosafot, חציה שנית, chetzyo shenis, says
קצת קשה. ktzas kasha. מנא לן דלא פליג רבי אבהו אף על
דא? mena lan d'lo palig Rabbi Abahu af al da? How do
you know Rabbi Abahu, right, that seems to be reasonable? If you
asked any of you before coming here, okay you all
know about a קנין הגבהה. kinyan hagbahah. What would you say about
a tallis that's half on the ground and half on a table
and you lifted the part off the ground fully off the ground?
Does that work or not? I think half of us would say,
maybe all of us would say, yeah that sounds like that should
work, that sounds like a good קנין הגבהה, kinyan hagbahah, which is
what רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu is saying. Okay, you didn't lift all
of it, but it's all right now off the ground and in
theory you could bring the rest of it towards you. Okay, so
that's what רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu says seems totally reasonable, and that's
why he says the guy is קונה koneh the reins, but the
גמרא Gemara considers that to be absurd, it's not a קנין הגבהה
kinyan hagbahah and therefore it says nobody is קונה koneh the reins.
Yes, Charlie?
Some things are such as the reins are impractical,
you're not going to be able to lift the rein that's connected
to the donkey's head.
I know, well that's the point here.
Yeah, but and a garment the same way, some pieces of cloth
are going to be so big that nobody could lift them.
Right, well, I mean there's other ways you could be קונה koneh
it or you could wrap it up and lift it or whatever,
but correct.
Isn't רש"י Rashi assuming here that the guy on the ground pulls
it and it comes off the head of the animal?
Well that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
Right, but רש"י Rashi says מראש החמור. merosh hachamor. Yeah, you're right,
רש"י Rashi does sound like even though it's attached,
somehow it's come off and he's got an advantage because he doesn't
pull up, he pulls down.
I understand, yeah, no, that we talked about, that רש"י Rashi said
because it starts suspended it works better than if it's on the
ground. It sounds
like according, but it does sound like
according to רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu even if it was physically currently
attached to the donkey then you have to literally be able to
yank it off of the donkey's head. But רש"י Rashi also says
that according to רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu even if it was all
on the ground and I lifted half, if I could yank the
rest it would work. I'm not so sure. It seems to me
that רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu is only saying it because it's all
suspended. But either way the גמרא Gemara rejects רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abahu.
Okay, even though that conceptually made a lot of sense and was
a nice explanation of the ברייתא, for whatever reason the גמרא Gemara
rejects it. Okay, back to the question of whether רוכב works. תא
שמע. רבי אליעזר אומר. Rabbi Eliezer omer. רוכב בשדה ומנהיג בעיר קנה.
rochev basadeh u'manhig ba'ir kana. If a guy is riding in the
field where it's natural to ride or leading in the city, in
the city people don't ride, it's considered not to be צנוע tzanua
the way רש"י Rashi says it. Okay, you know, you lead your
animal in the city, also maybe it's considered dangerous, you know, to
be, I think
in Rome you were not allowed to ride on animals in the
city itself. Do you know anything about that, Charlie?
That sounds right. Yeah, it was too crowded. Exactly.
Exactly.
Okay, anyway, so here again we get the question about if you
do things in an unnatural way. קנה. So presumably the point being
that it sounds like that
if you were to be riding it in the city it would
not work. Presumably leading it in a field would work, but riding
in a city or a town would be not natural and would
not work.
Anyway, but you see that riding works. הכא נמי מנהיג. hacha nami
manhig. No, we're not talking about just sitting, we're talking about riding,
we're talking about sitting and using your legs to make it move.
Okay, מנהיג ברגליו. manhig b'raglav. אי הכי, ei hachi, says the גמרא,
Gemara היינו מנהיג. hainu manhig. So why do you have to tell
me רוכב and מנהיג, manhig the two forms of מנהיג? manhig, תרי
גווני מנהיג. trei gavnei manhig. There's two types of מנהיג manhig, and
they don't both work in both places. אי הכי, רוכב בעיר מאי
טעמא לא קני? rochev ba'ir mai ta'ama lo kani? So why is
it, if it's basically just a form of מנהיג, manhig then why
is it that it doesn't work in the city, in the town?
אמר רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana, לפי שאין דרכן של בני אדם
לרכוב בעיר. lefi she'ein darkan shel bnei adam lirkov ba'ir. Okay, I
sort of gave that away ahead of time. That people don't naturally
ride in the town, so therefore even though if it were like
a weak קנין, kinyan, they're just sitting on
it. תוספות Tosafot says, maybe we would have understood it if you're
just sitting on it. You're just sitting on it in a city
and there's so many people around in the city, you're sitting on
it isn't anything, it's like not moving and you're just, you know,
it's meaningless. Maybe out in the field you're sitting on it, you
know, and it moves a little bit more because you're sitting on
it. But if רוכב means you're literally making it move. riding it
and making it move, then the גמרא Gemara says, then it should
work just as well in the town. So it says, no, no,
no, it's a different reason. It's cause it's not a natural thing
to do, sort of like the discussion before about the donkey and
the camel. Maybe doing it in a way that's not natural, especially
a way that's not natural
that is seen as for whatever reason not demonstrating ownership, okay, that
you're not going to be קונה. koneh. לפי שאין דרכן של בני
אדם לרכוב בעיר. lefi she'ein darkan shel b'nei adam lirkov ba'ir. אמר
ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא אלא מעתה. amar lei Rav Ashi l'Rav
Kahana ela mei'ata. So now we're going to challenge this: when is
doing an act of a קנין kinyan in a weird way not
an act of a
קנין? kinyan הגביה ארנקי בשבת, higbia arneki b'shabbos, let's say you lifted
up a wallet on שבת Shabbos to be קונה koneh it. שאין
דרכן של בני אדם להגביה ארנקי בשבת. she'ein darkan shel b'nei adam
lehagbia arneki b'shabbos. Most people don't handle wallets on שבת. Shabbos. הכא
נמי דלא קני? hacha nami d'lo kani? Would you say it doesn't
work? If it's a קנין, Kinyan it's a קנין. So if רכוב
rachuv means מנהיג, manhig, it's a real classic מנהיג manhig and you're
getting it to move, so then why shouldn't it work if you
do it in the town? אלא מאי עבד עבד. ela mai avad
avad.
By the wallet, if you did it, you did it. You violated
שבת Shabbos but you did it, and it works, you're קונה. koneh.
הכא נמי מאי דעבד עבד. hacha nami mai d'avad avad. So you
did a weird thing, you rode a donkey in a town, but
it should work, וקני. v'kani. Okay, so if it's a real קנין,
so it should work even in the town. If we're talking about
a real classic מנהיג, and
you could have referred to the discussion before about מנהיג and מושך
by camel and a donkey.
אלא, ela, you're right. By
מציאה, metzia, it would always work. But what are we talking about?
במקח וממכר עסקינן. b'mekach u'memkar askinan. We're not talking about a מציאה,
metzia, we're talking about a sale. דאמר ליה קני כדרך בני אדם
קונים. d'amar lei kani k'derech b'nei adam konim. And the seller put
on an explicit restriction and said, do it in a normal way.
Okay, which is like a really out, because it doesn't sound like
that. Okay. So this is interesting, right? If you look at the
camel and the donkey, the leading and the driving, there there was
a debate, did it have to be normal, and the גמרא Gemara
in the end said one way is just considered particularly not natural,
doesn't work. Okay, whereas here the גמרא Gemara pushes back and says
just because it's not natural, if you're really making it move, it
totally should work, okay, but there's a little bit of a difference.
Like here it might be natural for the animal, just not natural
for the setting. And that's why the גמרא's Gemara saying is, if
you're riding an animal, that's a total natural way to demonstrate ownership.
Just because it's not natural for the setting and it takes place
in the town, why should that not be good? And the גמרא's
Gemara answer is fine, it is good, but we're talking about a
special case where the person sold it and stipulated that you have
to do it in a way which is natural. Okay, and now
the גמרא Gemara adds some other stipulations. ואי רשות הרבים היא קני,
v'ei rishus harabim hi kani, but if you're doing it in the
public domain, not in a side street, that would work even in
a town. ואי אדם חשוב הוא קני, v'ei adam chashuv hu kani,
if you were an important person, then it works because important people,
they don't go leading their donkeys,
they will ride it, even though it's a little funny. It's not
considered צנוע tzanua to ride a donkey in town, but it's also
considered beneath an important person to lead his donkey. So therefore it's
what? Not צנוע tzanua
part? No, that's the way רש"י Rashi explains.
רש"י Rashi says, where's רש"י? Rashi? רש"י Rashi says before, משום צניעותא,
mishum tzniyusa, bottom of פ"ח
ע"א. peh ches amud aleph. And I don't know, I really have
no idea why.
Maybe it's like crowded and you have more control if you're leading
it.
And then if you're אדם חשוב, adam chashuv, then people
get out of your way.
And people get out of your way, maybe, okay, maybe. ואי אדם
חשוב הוא קני, v'ei adam chashuv hu kani, it worked, it's natural.
ואי אשה היא קניא. v'ei isha hi kanyia. So why by a
woman does it work? רש"י Rashi says because
it's easier for a woman to control an animal while riding it
than while leading it. That's what רש"י Rashi says.
Right,
so now it would be less צנוע tzanua for a woman, right.
I know. ואי זילא הוא קני, v'ei zila hu kani, or if
you are a lowly person, it works because then you're not afraid,
this is what רש"י Rashi says, of embarrassing yourself by riding it
because you're a lowly person anyway. So somehow it's acceptable for an
honorable person to do or for a lowly person to do, but
not for your average citizen. Don't ask me. Moving on. Okay, anyway,
here was a case where it sounded like רכוב rachuv is קונה,
koneh, but again, any evidence that רכוב rachuv, is קונה, koneh, the
גמרא Gemara, could just say we're talking about מנהיג ברגליו. You're not
just sitting on it, you're getting it to move, which is a
normal רכוב, and then it's actually pretty obvious that it's קונה. koneh.
Okay. בעי רבי אלעזר. ba'ei Rabi Elazar. רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar asks,
האומר לחברו משוך בהמה זו לקנות כלים שעליה. ha'omer l'chaveiro meshach beheima
zo liknos keilim she'aleha. You tell your friend, drag this animal in
order to take possession of the vessels on it. I'm not selling
you the donkey, I'm just selling you the wares on the donkey,
and drag the donkey and you'll be קונה koneh the wares.
מהו, mahu, what's the הלכה? So first the גמרא Gemara just has
a problem with the phrasing of it. לקנות, liknos, in order to
be קונה. koneh. מי אמר ליה קני? mi amar lei kani? He
didn't say, drag this donkey and be קונה. koneh. It's drag this
animal for the purpose, I don't know, somehow we say, oh, that
just means like you do it because you want to be קונה.
koneh. I'm not saying I'm actually being מקנה makne to you, which
seems pretty bizarre. If I'm telling you drag this in order to
be קונה. koneh. why I should not interpret that to mean that
I am telling you that with this you will be קונה koneh
sounds a little strange. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says fine. אלא,
Ela, you like fine, that phrasing is bothering you, I'll adjust the
phrase. משוך בהמה זו וקני כלים שעליה. Meshok behemah zu ve'kni keilim
she'alehah. Fine, I tell you drag this donkey and be קונה koneh
the vessels on it, what's the story? Now תוספות Tosfos says what's
the question? If I'm dragging the donkey, I'm dragging the vessels, and
משיכה meshichah works by vessels, so what's the issue? So תוספות Tosfos
says the issue is is because when I do a משיכה meshichah.
on an inanimate object, my power is totally causing the object to
move. I'm shlepping it. If I do a משיכה on a donkey,
for example, I'm not shlepping the donkey, I yank on the reins
and the donkey moves by itself. So here, that works for a
donkey because that's natural. But here, I did not
shlep the bags of grain, right? I yanked on the donkey and
the donkey moved the bags of grain. Is that a משיכה for
me to be קונה koneh the bags of grain? That's the question.
Okay. So will that work or not? So the גמרא Gemara, is
not going to answer the question, it's going to digress. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says או לא. o lo. So אמר רבא, אי
אמר ליה קני בהמה וקני כלים מי קני כלים? Amar Rava ee
amar lei kni behemah u'kni keilim mi kani keilim? רבא Rava says
look, it's so funny, it's like a Jew answers a question with
a question. We completely avoid answering it. First we said, oh, you
said לקנות, liknos, you can't say לקנות. liknos. Okay, fine, he says
קני. Oh, wait a minute. You're asking about if you're just being
קונה koneh the bags of grain, why weren't you asking about a
scenario where I'm telling you be קונה koneh the donkey and the
grain? Presumably in that case, you're taking it for granted that it
will work if you're trying to be קונה koneh both. Well, that's
not so obvious that it will work if you're trying to be
קונה koneh both. Why should that be any better? Why do you
think if you're being קונה koneh the donkey, why am I asking
the case only are you קונה koneh the grain alone? Why should
it be more obvious if I say be קונה koneh the donkey
with the grain that you should be קונה koneh both? Okay. So
what would you think? Why do you think that that might be
more obvious?
Well,
you could either conceptualize it as one big thing, like it's really
the donkey with its grain, and like we were discussing before, so
if the קנין works for the donkey and I'm willing to sell
you both, we look at it all as like as a piece
of the donkey. But what the גמרא Gemara. understands is is that
the reason you would be קונה, koneh, it's רבא Rava thinks that
it's more obvious you should be קונה koneh both is because then
once I own the donkey, the donkey is my object, it's like
my חצר, chatzer, and then the grain is in my property on
top of my donkey, and I'm קונה koneh because of a קנין
חצר. kinyan chatzer. So רבא Rava says you're asking the question about
being קונה koneh the grain alone, sounds like you're taking it for
granted that if you're קונה koneh the donkey and the grain, that
definitely does work. That's not so fast! Not necessarily. אי אמר, Ee
amar, so רבא, Rava, so let's take a look.
אמר רבא Amar Rava, אי אמר ליה קני בהמה וקני כלים מי
קני כלים? Ee amar lei kni behemah u'kni keilim mi kani keilim?
What do you think that if you said be קונה koneh both,
it definitely does work? That's not so obvious. חצר מהלכת היא. Chatzer
mehalekhes hi. That could only work, he's not conceptualizing it as one
unit, again maybe that could be conceptualized if it's something like the
reins or the saddle, but here it's some a load on the
donkey that's not conceptualized as one unit. So if you that should
be קונה, koneh, it's because the donkey becomes yours and then you're
קונה koneh the bags of grain with a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer.
But one minute, it's a moving courtyard, it's a moving yard. חצר
מהלכת לא קניא. Chatzer mehalekhes lo kanyah. The only type of a
חצר chatzer that works, we based on another discussion in a different
גמרא, Gemara is if the חצר chatzer is not moving. A moving
חצר chatzer isn't קונה. koneh. וכי תימא כשעמדה, Ve'chi teima ke'she'amdah, you'll
say, oh well, if the donkey stops, then the yard is isn't
moving, so then I can be קונה koneh it. No. וכל שאילו
מהלך לא קניא, Ve'chol she'ilu mehalech lo kanyah, our principle is that
if something could be moving and therefore you wouldn't be קונה koneh
because it's a moving piece of property, so עומד ויושב לא קניא,
omed ve'yoshev lo kanyah, it's also doesn't work even if it happens
to be standing or sitting. So anything that has the ability to
be moving is not enough of property under my control to be
worked to allow me to be קונה koneh things that are on
it. So why is it obvious to you that if you were
being קונה koneh the donkey you were קונה koneh that if you
were also קונה koneh the donkey, you would get the grain with
it? That shouldn't work. That's not necessarily a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer.
So גמרא Gemara says והלכתא ve'hilchosa what?
So here now we've got into קנין חצר kinyan chatzer and we've
completely moved out of the משיכה.
That's what I was saying. We've avoided the question. I asked a
question of does it work on the bags of grain? And rather
than answering my question, the first thing you do is you give
me a hard time about the phrasing. Then the next thing you
do is you're talking about whether it would work if you did
both of them together. And the גמרא Gemara. is never going to
come back to answer the first question.
I thought that we were comfortable saying if an animal's moving, there's
some sort of קנין with the bridle. Right. I don't know if
specifically.
Right. Like, yeah, I mean why is the גמרא, Gemara well, so
there was a מציאה, metzi'ah, right?
Well, תוספות Tosfos says that the question there about the my whether
my moving helps you with the reins is to some degree based
on this discussion here
of רב אשי, Rav Ashi, right, that the person who was moving
the animal was קונה koneh in half the bridle.
Right, so תוספות Tosafos says that that discussion was a little bit
based on this discussion here.
Yeah, but over there we're normally talking about מציאה, Metziyah, right? It's
not מקח וממכר? Makkach Umimkar?
No, we're talking about, oh, yeah, we're talking about מקח וממכר.
Makkach Umimkar. So are you telling me, this is מקח וממכר, Makkach
Umimkar, so I have a trucking company, you've ordered some grain, I
put your grain in my truck to deliver it, that's a חצר
מהלכת. Chatzer Mehalechet. Right, my truck. You're saying it's possible that I'm
קונה Koneh the grain that's in my truck that I'm delivering to
you?
How?
How else would you be קונה? Koneh?
No, no, no, right,
in other words, what's,
what, you're saying
a third party is contracted to deliver it.
No, you can't be קונה Koneh something against the will of the
parties. So the question, if everybody wants to transfer it, the question
is does it work? Everybody is trying to effect a transfer. You're
trying to transfer your grain to me, and it's honey on your
donkey's back, and when I take possession of your donkey, and when
I move your donkey, have I yet done a מעשה קנין Maaseh
Kinyan on your grain? You're trying to transfer it to me,
I'm already קונה Koneh your grain along with your animal.
You're talking about that five second moment between you pulling the donkey
and actually removing the grain off the saddlebags?
Exactly, if something happens after I've moved the donkey but before I've
actually taken the bags and taken them into my house. Yeah, that's
what we're always talking about, when is the exact moment that the
קנין takes place? So רבא's Rava question was, does it, or whoever's
question it was, was Rabbi Eliezer, was does it
take place if I got the donkey to move but I didn't
directly shove the grains, it's just the grain moved because it was
on the donkey's back. And רבא Rava avoids answering the question and
says, well why aren't you asking about if you're selling the donkey
and the grain together? Sounds like you assume that that works, but
that doesn't work, because the donkey doesn't work as a קנין חצר,
Kinyan Chatzer, yeah.
I don't see how an animal can be a חצר Chatzer at
all in the way that they use leading with
saddlebags and also if there is a side of the animal not
the top.
That's an interesting question. I'm not sure that would matter but I
hear the point. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this: והלכתא
Vehilchasa fine. Why would we assume, why weren't we asking about the
case when you were selling both the donkey and the grain? Because
there are cases that that would work as a קנין חצר. Kinyan
Chatzer. Where would that work as a קנין חצר? Kinyan Chatzer? בכפותה.
B'kfusa. If the animal was bound, so it couldn't walk even if
it wanted to. Okay, so we've digressed and said why aren't you
talking about the case where it's on the donkey, presumably where you're
selling also the donkey, presumably you assume that case it does work,
but that really shouldn't work. The answer is fine, there are cases
of that that it would work when the animal was bound up
and it couldn't move, then you're ממש Mamash שלעפינג Schlepping the whole
thing, then it should work on the grain too, because then you're
just שלעפינג Schlepping the whole thing. But anyway you still haven't answered
the initial question. Now we're going to keep on digressing about the
moving חצר. Chatzer. אמר ליה רב פפא לרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
לרבא, Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua l'Rava, so
רב הונא, Rav Huna, רב פפא Rav Pappa and רב הונא Rav
Huna said to רבא, Rava, אלא מעתה Ela Me'atah האי מהלכת בספינה,
Hai mehalechet b'sfina, רבא Rava you're saying that you can't be קונה
Koneh a moving חצר, Chatzer, even if it's natural for it to
move? So if you're going on your boat, it's you own the
boat, it's your property, קפצו דגים ונחו בתוכה ספינה, Kafzu dagim venachu
b'tocha sfina,
and some fish flew into flying fish flew into your boat, okay,
and they're now on your boat, on your property, you would say,
הכא נמי דחצר מהלכת ולא קני? Hacha nami dechatzer mehalechet v'lo kani?
You'd say you wouldn't be קונה Koneh because the boat is a
moving חצר? Chatzer? אמר ליה Amar lei no, ספינה מנח נייח, Sfina
minach nayach, no,
the boat is stationary, it's not moving on its own accord, it
doesn't propel itself, ומיא היא דקממטו לה, Umaya hi deka mamtu lah,
the water is just moving underneath it. Okay, even if it's got
oars or it's got an engine, you as a human being are
moving the boat. The boat itself is an inanimate unmoving object left
to its own devices. You can totally understand this. If I am
a human being because the other case of חצר מהלכת Chatzer Mehalechet
is a slave, or if we're dealing with a human being or
if we're dealing with an animal, so they have will of their
own, they move themselves, so to the degree that I say something
on this human being and on this animal is on my property
and I'm in control of it
when that animal's will or that human being's will can choose to
move and get out of my control, I totally understand it. A
car would work? A car would work, I'm the one who moves
the car, exactly. A cart? A cart, yeah. Attached to a horse?
Sure. Yeah, a cart that's attached to the horse would work. I
would say yes. Okay, wait let's see the next case in the
גמרא. Okay. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi,
רביינא Ravina said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אלא מעתה Ela Me'atah
היתה מהלכת ברשות הרבים, Haisa mehalechet b'reshus harabbim, a woman was going
in רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabbim, וזרק לה גט לתוך חיקה או לתוך
קלתה, Vezarka haget l'toch cheika o l'toch kalsah, and somebody threw a
גט Get into her like into her cloak or into her the
hat on her head, the basket on her head, הכא נמי דלא
מיגרשה? Hacha nami d'lo migarsha?
Would you say
it's not because the basket is moving? So the same answer. אמר
ליה Amar lei התם מנח נייח,
Tasam minach nayach, ואיהי דקא מסגיא. V'ee deka masgi masgia. No, the
basket is stationary. She's moving the basket. The basket, okay, which makes
total sense, it doesn't mean that... it cannot and that's why it
doesn't matter if the animal happens to be standing. The problem is
not the fact that it's stationary or moving. The problem is is
whether it moves on its own accord, whether it's able to move
through its own will, okay? And if something can move on its
own will, it's not totally under my control that it works as
a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So we had a nice little digression
about קנין חצר, kinyan chatzer, and we never got back to answer
the question, which is: If I
move the donkey and I'm not קונה koneh the donkey, but I
cause the grain on the donkey's back to move, is that also
a קנין משיכה kinyan meshichah on the grain? And we never answered
that question. Yeah. Why is she not מגורשת? megureshet? He raised his
hand. She is מגורשת. megureshet. It was a rhetorical question. Okay. So
a cart or a wagon or car or truck is a חצר.
chatzer. Correct. Or the... so does that apply to Shabbat laws as
well? Yes, yes, there is an interesting question the גמרא has about
something that's stationary—like if I throw something onto a—onto onto something that's
floating. Is that considered that I placed it down in a stationary
way on Shabbat because it's stationary vis-a-vis the thing it's on, but
not vis-a-vis the large, the area surrounding it. Okay, anyway. So that's
what happens when people move on their own. Okay, anyway, moving on.
Okay. So, היה רוכב על גבי בהמה וראה מציאה. hayah rochev agabi
behemah vera'ah metziah. Now, we've been alluding to the discussion of מגביה
מציאה לחבירו, magbia metziah lechavero, picking up a מציאה metziah for your
friend—does it work? Now we're finally going to get to it through
a debate on how to interpret this next משנה. mishnah Okay, notice
by the way that this is—although the first משנה mishnah. is what
classic people think about בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, two people holding onto
something, arguing, how do you do a fair division? All this focus
on what's a fair division—in a way it's really a discussion in
the context of finding a
מציאה. metziah. And so classically the way a lot of מסכתות masechtos
begin is you don't start with some simple rule: Here's when you
get to keep a מציאה metziah that you find. No, no, you
start with some bizarre case. Two people find it at the same
time and they're arguing about it, who do you award it to?
Similarly here, we have a more unusual cases of מציאה metziah till
we get to the more classic ones that are coming up in
the second פרק. perek. Okay, so here's the case. היה רוכב על
גבי בהמה—you're hayah rochev agabi behemah riding on an animal—וראה מציאה—and vera'ah
metziah you saw, oh my gosh, 20 bucks, I see it lying
in the street in front of me. ואמר לחבירו—and ve'amar lechavero Charlie
here is not—is walking alongside of me, and I don't want to
get off of my donkey. So I say to Charlie, "תנה לי,
tenali, Charlie! Look, there's 20 bucks there, go take that for me."
Okay. נטלה—Charlie natlah picks up the 20
bucks—ואמר אני זכיתי בה—"Okay, ve'amar ani zachiti bah I got it, it's
mine." Okay. זכה בה—he zachah bah gets to keep it. All right.
Even though I told him to do it, he's entitled to pick
it up for
himself. Okay. אם משנתנה לו אמר אני זכיתי בה—but im mishenetnah lo
amar ani zachiti bah after Charlie gives me the 20 bucks he
says, "Actually when I picked it up I was picking it up
for myself," then לא אמר כלום—good lo amar klum luck Charlie, good
luck, try to prove that. Okay. Your claim means nothing once you've
given it to me. But if—but when it's—it was in your hand,
even though I asked you to do it, you did it for
yourself, that works. Okay. Now what's not spelled out here is, it
sounds like though if he picked it up for me, I am
קונה, koneh, right? It's only because he picked it up for himself.
And then he's believed as long as he's still in possession of
it. Okay, so that seems to be מגביה מציאה לחבירו קנה חבירו.
magbia metziah lechavero kanah chavero. Had he done it for me, it
would have worked. So let's see what the גמרא says.
Why should he not give him a finder's fee?
Right, no, there's no idea of a finder's fee or anything like
that. Right, that's like that first דף daf in the גמרא. It
says you might think that אני מצאתיה—"I ani metzatia saw it first."
But seeing it first does not entitle you to it. I know,
that's the surprising thing. Like it says like Charlie can pick it
up and he only saw it because I pointed it out to
him, and he's totally קונה, koneh, right? And it does—and once again,
it does not deal with the ethical issues involved in that. All
right. תנן התם—we tenan hatam taught over there. מי שליקט את
הפאה—somebody mi shelikat et ha-pe'ah picked up פאה—not pe'ah for himself. Okay,
the corner that's left for the עניים. ani'im. ואמר הרי זו לפלוני
עני—"I'm ve'amar harei zo leploni ani picking it up for Reuven the
poor person." רבי אליעזר אמר זכו לו—so Rabbi Eliezer amar zachu lo
that works, it now belongs to Reuven. וחכמים אומרים יתננה לעניים
שבראשון—no, vachachamim omrim yitnenah le'ani'im sheba'rishon it does not work and you
have to give it—you're not the owner of the field, by the
way. רש"י Rashi points out the owner of the field even if
you're an עני, ani, you cannot pick up your own grain. Okay,
but you're a third party. Okay, it did not work for Reuven,
and the first עני—it ani still remains פאה pe'ah and it's הפקר
hefker to any עניים, ani'im, and the first עני ani has a
right to it. All right. So this sounds like a case of
sort of like of a מגביה מציאה. magbia metziah. So אמר עולא—אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי: מחלוקת מעשיר
לעני—the machloket me'ashir le'ani debate is I'm a rich person and I'm—meaning
I'm not entitled to פאה, pe'ah, and I'm picking up the פאה
pe'ah for a poor person who is. רבי אליעזר סבר: Rabbi Eliezer
savar: Now in order for this to work, for me to pick
up the פאה pe'ah for Reuven, you have to do two—you have
to do two steps. What are the two steps? Number one: מיגו
דאי בעי מפקיר נכסיה והוי עני וחזי
ליה—in migo d'iba'i mafkar nichseh vehavei ani vechazi leh theory I could
pick up the פאה pe'ah for myself. Why? If I wanted to
renounce ownership of all my property and become an עני ani and
it would be fitting for me. a pauper, then I could in
theory do that, and then I'd be entitled to the פאה. pe'ah.
So, because theoretically the פאה pe'ah is relevant to me, not in
my current state, but I could be מפקיר mafkir all my money,
so אי בעי מפקר נכסיה הוי עני וחזי ליה השתא נמי חזי
ליה, ee ba'ee mafkir nikhsei vehavei ani vechazei lei hashta nami chazei
lei, then it's considered to be, since theoretically I could be in
a state where I could take possession, it's considered to be something
that in theory that is fit for me, for me to own,
and that's stage number one. And stage number two is ומיגו דזכי
לנפשיה, umigo dezachi lenafshei,
and since I in I could be קונה koneh for myself, if
I wanted to, זכי נמי לחבריה, zachi nami lachavreih, I'm entitled to
be זוכה zocheh for somebody else. So how can I pick it
up for ראובן? Reuven? It's not enough to say because I could
pick it up for myself and I could pick it up for
ראובן. Reuven. I can't in my current state. But I could get
myself into a state where I would be entitled to pick it
up, and then because in that state since I'd be entitled to,
I'm also now I could also now pick it up for ראובן.
Reuven. Two degrees removed. And therefore I can do it. רבנן סברי,
Rabbanan savri, and the Rabbis hold, חד מיגו אמרינן תרי מיגו לא
אמרינן. chad migo amrinan trei migo lo amrinan. No. If you were
an עני ani and you only had to do one step removed,
I could pick it for myself, I'll pick it up for someone
else, that would work. But two steps removed, I could become an
עני ani and I could pick it up for myself in theory,
that we won't say. That's one way of framing the debate, that
we're talking about a עשיר ashir is picking it up. So what
would that mean? It would mean אבל מעני לעני, aval me'ani le'ani,
if the guy picking it up himself was an
עני, ani, then דברי הכל זכה לו, divrei hakol zachah lo,
then everybody would agree it would work, because that's only one step
removed. דמיגו דזכי לנפשיה, demigo dezachi lenafshei,
since you could take possession for yourself, זכי נמי לחבריה, zachi nami
lachavreih, you can for somebody else. That's the case of מגביה מציאה
לחבריה. magbi'ah metzi'ah lachavreih. So one way of framing it is, everybody
agrees מגביה מציאה לחבריה magbi'ah metzi'ah lachavreih works, if you could take
it for yourself, you could take it for someone else, but the
question here is you can't take it for yourself in your current
state. One minute.
That's one way of framing. אמר ליה רב נחמן, amar lei Rav
Nachman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman said לעולא, le'Ulla, ולימא מר, veleima mar,
why are you framing it that way? Why not say מעני לעני
מחלוקת, me'ani le'ani machlokes, maybe we're assuming the guy picking it up
is also an עני. ani. They're both עניים, ani'im, the picking it
up and the one it's being picked up for. דהא, deha, and
the debate is, can you be מגביה מציאה לחבריה? magbi'ah metzi'ah lachavreih?
You could pick it up for yourself, are you entitled to pick
it up for someone else? And that's the debate whether you can
take the פאה pe'ah for another עני. ani. Okay. Now why should
I think there's a debate about מגביה מציאה? magbi'ah metzi'ah? Because he
says, let's look at our משנה. mishnah, That's what he thinks is
going on in our משנה, mishnah, that you can't pick it up
for somebody else. דמציאה, demetzi'ah,
a lost object, הכל עניים אצלה, hakol ani'im etzlah, everybody, it's like
one of those, you know, SAT analogies, poor person to פאה, pe'ah,
no, פאה pe'ah to poor person is like מציאה metzi'ah to everyone.
Okay, because, you know, every only poor people are allowed to take
פאה, pe'ah, but anyone can take a מציאה. metzi'ah. So everyone for
a מציאה metzi'ah is like a poor person. Everyone is entitled.
Okay, ותנן, utenan, and why should I think it doesn't work for
me to pick up a lost object for somebody else? היה רוכב
על גבי בהמה וראה מציאה ואמר לחבירו תנה לי, ha'hayah rochev al
gabei beheimah vera'ah metzi'ah ve'amar lechavero tenah li, you say to your
friend go get it, נטלה ואמר אני זכיתי בה, natalah ve'amar ani
zachisi bah, he says I took possession, זכה בה. zachah bah. Now
he thinks "I took possession" does not mean "I took possession first
when I picked it up." He thinks when Charlie comes and says
"I took possession of the 20 dollars," Charlie is saying to me,
"Yeah, I picked it up for you, but I've changed my mind.
I'm just going to keep it now." And until Charlie gives it
to me, he's reading the משנה, mishnah. once he gives it to
me he can't say that, but until the moment he gives it
to me, he can decide to just pocket it. Okay. Why should
that be? That's because מגביה מציאה לחבריה לא קנה חבירו. magbi'ah metzi'ah
lachavreih lo kanah chaveiro. That's how he's reading the משנה. mishnah Okay,
ואמר אני זכיתי בה זכה בה. ve'amar ani zachisi bah zachah bah.
אי אמרת בשלמא מעני לעני מחלוקת, ee amart bishlama me'ani le'ani machlokes,
if there's a debate even for an עני ani picking it up
for an עני, ani, that maybe according to one opinion you can't
do it, you can do it for yourself but you can't do
it for someone else,
מתניתין מני רבנן? masnisin mani Rabbanan? Then our משנה mishnah is the
רבנן. Rabbanan. They say you can't get פאה pe'ah for another עני,
ani, you can get it for yourself if you're an עני ani
but not for another one. And that's why in our משנה mishnah.
Charlie could have taken the 20 for himself, but if he initially
took it, I'm sorry did I read that wrong?
(רבנן Rabbanan say what? רבנן Rabbanan say you can't do it for
somebody else. Right.) So, I'm sorry, right. So, ah, so the רבנן
Rabbanan say you can't get the פאה pe'ah for someone else. So
Charlie also even if he was trying to get this the 20
dollars for me, it didn't work. And therefore he's always entitled to
keep it to himself. So מתניתין מני רבנן היא. masnisin mani Rabbanan
hi. Why can Charlie keep the 20 dollars even if he changed
his mind? That's how he's reading the משנה. Mishnah. Because מגביה מציאה
לחבריה magbi'ah metzi'ah lachavreih doesn't work. Okay, אלא אי אמרת בעשיר ועני
מחלוקת, ella ee amart be'ashir ve'ani machlokes, but if everybody agrees that
an עני ani can pick up for an עני, ani, and you
can pick up a מציאה metzi'ah for somebody else, and the only
question is if you're two stages removed, אבל מעני לעני דברי הכל
זכה לו, aval me'ani le'ani divrei hakol zachah lo, but if you're
a poor person you can pick פאה pe'ah for a poor person,
and if you get a מציאה metzi'ah you can pick a מציאה
metzi'ah for someone else if you see a מציאה. metzi'ah. So הא
מני? ha'mani? So why does Charlie get to keep the 20 dollars?
Because if he picked it up for me? לא רבנן ולא רבי
אליעזר. lo Rabbanan v'lo Rebbi Eliezer. According to this, both the Rabbis
and רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
say that if you're an עני, ani, you can pick פאה pe'ah
for someone else. And if you have a מציאה, metziah, you can
take it for someone else. So if everybody agrees מגביה מציאה לחברו
קנה חברו, magbi'ah metziah l'chavero kanah chavero, why does Charlie get to
keep the twenty dollars when he changes his mind? He picked it
up for me. And the answer is the גמרא says, אמר ליה,
amar lei, מתניתין דאמר תחילה. matnitin d'amar techilah. No, Charlie, when Charlie
says I'm taking it for myself, he's not changed his mind. Charlie
says when he comes back with the twenty dollars to me, he
says I picked it up initially for myself. That's I think how
we read the משנה. Mishnah? Okay, so that's the question. How do
you read the משנה? Mishnah The משנה Mishnah says Charlie can say
I picked it up for myself, it's mine. So one way of
reading the משנה Mishnah is even if he picks it up for
me, he can then change his mind and say I'm keeping it.
Reading that, the משנה Mishnah is telling you מגביה מציאה לחברו לא
קנה חברו. magbi'ah metziah l'chavero lo kanah chavero. Even if he picked
it up for me, I don't own it yet, and he can
change his mind until he hands it over. And the other way
of reading it is no, he's only entitled to keep it if
he claimed he initially picked it up for himself. But if he
admits he picked it up for me, I own it because מגביה
מציאה לחברו קנה חברו. magbi'ah metziah l'chavero kanah chavero. So that issue
that we've been debating, discussing all along, it depends how you read
this משנה and what Charlie is claiming when he says that he's
keeping it. Okay, so we'll pick up with this tomorrow.